[music]
[music] signal
and speak.
>> Dr. Barry Chaken is not just a physician
leader. He's a strategic and a longtime
advocate for meaningful healthc care
change with more than 25 years of
experience in clinical transformation
health IT and public health. He's worked
across payer provider and policy
domains. Barry served as chief medical
officer under m multiple health tech
companies advised the federal government
on pandemic preparedness and is a past
board chair of HIMS. He also is the
founder of DocsNetwork, a consultancy
focused on clinical innovation and
patient safety. But beyond his resume,
Barry brings a steady voice on the
ethical use of technology, the culture
of care,
and the human moments that often get
lost in the machinery of healthcare
systems. In this conversation, we talk
about what it takes to lead with
integrity, how to challenge orthodoxy in
times of change, and why he still
believes healthc care is a calling. Dr.
Barry Chaken, welcome to the Signal
Room.
>> Thank you so much, Chris. I really
appreciate that introduction.
>> Well, it it's an honor to have you. I've
known you for a number of years and it's
just exciting to be able to launch the
Signal Room with a with a good friend
and a visionary at the same time. So
again, thank you and welcome. We've
touched a little bit about what I would
consider being AI ready. Um this is a
big cultural adjustment that an
organization will have to go through. So
for hospital and health system leaders
that are tuning in, what's the first
organizational change that they should
make to become AI ready? Identify
a goal that you want to achieve. Make
sure you don't forget what that goal is
and explore AI technology with other
changes and adaptations you need to make
to be able to achieve that goal. Do not
say, "Oh, I'm going to have an AI plan
and implement AI."
>> It has to solve a particular problem or
it has to improve your quality of care,
your capacity, whatever around your
organization. That's the most important
thing. Understand what the goal is and
deliver the goal. I'll tell you, I think
we all kind of know this. Big projects
have a high propensity probability of
failing. So why choose a big project?
Choose a small project, execute on it,
learn from it, make it a success, and
then do a second one using what you
learned from the first one, and go on
and on. That said, unless you're a large
academic medical center, you probably
don't have the resources to start
developing your own AI. You're going to
have to buy it from a technology vendor.
If you're going to do that, make sure to
your the best of your ability, you test
every assumption and every suggestion
that they make and ask them as if you
were a three-year-old or four-year-old,
why? Why? Why?
>> Right?
>> It's the why and the how. Try. If you do
not understand what they're doing for
you, that means that they don't
understand what they're doing for you.
You need to be able to understand
everything they tell you and answer
every question and don't let them
obiscate. And I'm not saying that the IT
organizations are going to do this.
>> All I'm saying is AI is so complicated.
It's difficult for those experts, the
Altman's of the world to understand how
AI works. And he's the founder of OpenAI
chat GPT. If he doesn't understand it,
how can you expect to understand it in
the in that detail? But what we can do
is take the proper steps to understand
it as best we can, get the explanations
as best we can. That decreases the
likelihood that we're going to have a
problem. So essentially, we don't
transform because it's transformation
and that's the that's the end goal. It's
still really all about what healthc care
starts ends with and it's that the human
interaction and it's about taking care
of people. And you know, one of the
things that I have a great deal of
respect for is people like you who took
took the hypocratic oath. First, do no
harm. It's not about the the technology
that we can bring to bear. It's how the
technology can be used to support the
mission. And I I I love the clarity that
you speak with on that. Kind of leans
into something else that's a a little
challenging to to really work through.
And I think as we're talking about
readiness, there's a bunch of things
that we have to look at. And does it
check this box? this box and this box.
This kind of gets into some of the more
sensitive areas. So there's growing
concern around algorithmic bias as you
mentioned bias in healthcare. How do you
see governance evolving to address
equity and ethics with AI?
>> Um well there's a
uh a divide between what the United
States wants to do and what say Europe
wants to do. The recent announcement
from the administration around AI, it
was I think it was uh about a week or so
ago was solely focused on go as fast as
you pos possibly can and don't worry too
much about the consequences. There's
about 20% of people who live and die
with AI in their life. They think about
all the time who think that uh general
artificial intelligence will destroy
humanity. So, I'm not going to tell your
audience how they should think of this
problem. I'm just going to say the
United States has a particular
perspective about going as fast as we
can and we can worry about it later. The
European Union on the other hand
understands the need to compete with
China for example and AI technology but
understands some of those risks and have
a little bit more constraints on that.
Um my own opinion is that
AI run a muck is quite dangerous in so
many ways right
>> um politically there were about 160
elections around the world last year and
almost all of them were influenced by
deep fakes artificial intelligence you
know fake images fake videos and stuff
um I'm not sure that we as humans are
going to be able to
discern what's real and what's fake. And
that
>> scares the heck out of me because if we
don't trust each other, which is the
foundation, the bedrock of society, and
we get to a place where all we do is
disagree and believe fake videos and
such, we don't trust each other, society
breaks down. Let me share one quick
thing with you. Sometime in the last
couple of years, you've been at a coffee
shop, you've been in a shopping center,
you've been in a grocery store, and you
needed to leave your bag in the shopping
cart or at the table as you went up to
get a stir for your coffee or something
you forgot to pick up on the cereal
aisle for your child,
>> right? And you never wondered at one
second that the person who you asked to
watch your bag or watch your cart was
going to take something from you. Never.
We inherently as human beings trust
people. That's what makes us human. If
we do things and AI has a risk of of
eroding that if we lose that then we use
lose our humanity. In a sense we lose
our society.
So let's be careful about that and how
we use artificial intelligence.
>> Yeah, that's a that's a huge huge
challenge. You know, having countries
make different decisions around how
they're going to deploy it and the pace
that they're going to go. It does put us
in a really interesting position because
healthcare in the United States is not
only impacting citizens of our country,
it's impacting people who visit here
too. and you know things like GDPR
uh in Europe, you know, the patient has
some level of ownership of their data
and they can actually say yay or nay in
terms of where they want it and how they
want it to be used. So what role should
patients actually have in AI development
in deployment? I mean, how are we going
to earn their trust and invite their
voice into the design process? Because
it seems like that's something that
would be the right thing for us to do.
Having worked for tech companies, I
think it's going to have to happen at
the provider organization level. You'll
probably see a bit of it also in pharma
because they have the resources to be
able to do that. I don't think the tech
companies are connected that way to
involve patients in the development of
their products. I probably see their
clients as being responsible for that.
Even if you're a small community
hospital, it doesn't require a lot of
resources to bring some people in and
have them part of the planning process.
Um,
I think everyone who lives in a
community with a community hospital,
particularly in suburban or rural areas
are vested very much in that facility
and therefore I think they'll
participate to help the organization
make the right tools,
uh, choose the right tools and make the
right decisions on using the AI. So just
involve them and if anything you're just
bring your community together in in your
institution that is incredibly important
to their health and survival. I think
that's a another really great call out.
It's a it's a different type of
responsibility that we need to own in
healthcare. Um a patient needs to be
able to understand enough to make an
informed decision around whether they're
comfortable. Not everyone's going to
want to be disclosing that they're using
AI. I think in health care because of
the these ethical standards and the
commitment as a physician that you make.
There's something that we have to do
there. And I think the communication and
that education, we've got to come up
with really some some great simple ways
to make sure that that happens without
adding yet another layer on the
complexity of what a physician actually
needs to do in in that encounter because
a patient's going to be much more
comfortable trusting their physician's
explanation than they are from from
maybe I'm the guy at the front desk and
I don't really understand it, but I'm
going to try to make it sure the patient
does. Those are some things we have to
kind of think through together. Um both
from an administrator, an executive
standpoint and a clinician standpoint
and even our nurses. We need to kind of
think through that and where does that
messaging happen and how uh when you run
an organization particularly one like
healthcare, you have to think of it as a
community and if you're a part of senior
leadership, you have to make them people
who work for you feel part of the
community,
>> right? Um, I've always believed that uh
much of people's self-worth when they're
in working age is the work that they do.
Sure, they like getting their salary and
getting their bonuses bonuses and all of
that. And most people are most
concerned, do I have enough to put the
food on the table, have a roof over my
head, take care of my children? That's
the way they look at it.
They want to feel involved. You need to
go if you're senior leadership just to
make those people who work there feel
important and seen and you will get a
lot more happy employees which then mean
happy customers or happy patients. It's
incredibly important. Um being connected
to the people who report eventually
report up to you. With AI, you want to
emphasize the concept of trust. Well, do
things to make sure the people in your
organization feel important and wanted.
And it's not having a nice holiday
party. It's not about
>> right
>> so much about giving out a a an increase
in a in a bonus. That's all nice, but
those go away really quickly. It's the
day-to-day feeling of you're involved.
I'm contributing. I'm making my
organization successful. And on top of
that, I'm serving my community, my
neighbors.
>> I love that. That's really the probably
one of the biggest things that our tech
partners can understand about what what
we need them to help us do. Um they're
part of our communities too. So are the
investors who are wanting to help us uh
really develop the right solutions. If
all of us are about that community and
taking care of the people that we are in
that community with, I think we have a
lot of opportunities and I I'm excited
about the future for if we can get this
right. Um, so looking ahead to 2050,
back to your the concept of your book,
what's your most optimistic prediction
of how AI will improve care and what
worries you the most?
>> Okay, let's talk about the positive
first. Okay,
>> I love that. Excuse me. I think First AI
is going to do amazing things at
discovering new ways to treat patients.
Uh, pharmaceutical developments and
acceleration is going to be tremendous.
And that's magical. Alpha 2, alpha 3 and
AlphaFold, you know, creates understanding,
understanding how proteins fold. That
doesn't sound important, but everything
that happens in biology is around
proteins. And then being able to predict
how proteins interact with each other,
molecules interact with each other is an
enormous advantage. It can quickly
accelerate uh drug development. And then
of course clinical trials identifying
people who are novel patients who have
not been treated yet to enter into a
clinical trial where today once you've
been treated you may no longer be
eligible for a trial. So that gets
people involved reaching out outside of
the academic medical centers to identify
those people and get them involved. We
can use AI to be able to do that to
redesign the model to do a clinical
trial in silico, meaning in a computer
using digital people right they'll take
whoever you are create you digitally
will understand your genetics and all
the other things that make you make you
who you are and do a clinical trial in
silico and run it that way to see how
the molecules and the proteins will
interact in biology. That obviously is
going to greatly accelerate all this
work and development. And then of course
the research we can do in terms of how
to do surgeries and how to do take care
of patients and do physical therapy and
others all that's going to be great. I
think if we deploy a prop AI properly
we'll be able to have a much better
relationship between the caregiver and
the patient and the patient and the
organization. Today, it's extremely
expensive to hire people to be on the
phone, to interact with you, to remind
you to come in for your your
appointment, to do the proper things
before your surgery or postsurgical
care, to take your medications. So much
of that can be personalized that before
we couldn't do that.
>> Um, we can decrease the variation in how
care is delivered the same way using AI.
Everyone should not be treated the same
way, but some people shouldn't be
treated at all that way. And we can be
able to decrease that variation and
personalize it in a simple way. A busy
single mother with three children is
unlikely to be able to take a medication
four times a day, even though that's the
best treatment for her. So, why don't we
go ahead and do something? Did you hear
that? You didn't hear it. Okay, let me
start again. It's because my Anyway, it
was playing music and I thought it came
through the mic. So, you'll edit this
thing.
Um, you have a single mother who has
three children and is working. It's
really hard for her to take her
medication four times a day, even though
that is the first line of defense for
her illness. Right?
>> So, the AI can understand that and say,
I think with Sally, she should take this
pill, which is in the morning and at
night. That'll fit into her schedule. It
is not the best, but it's more likely
she'll take that medication. she'll get
some benefit from it. So that's really
important and the just the interaction
where the organization can be
personalized the messaging to those
patients is great to motivate them to
follow their regimen to come into the
organization to feel seen because you
can personalize it in ways that we don't
have people that can actually
personalize. What's the downside? My
biggest fear is using AI solely to
generate revenue and not worrying about
the outcomes that happen for those
patients. And the second thing is making
mistakes in clinical errors through
automation bias with poorly designed
workflows or AI that is not properly
trained for the population that is being
seen in the organization that is
utilizing it. For example, New York City
has a very diverse population. If you
trained the AI models on people from
Oklahoma or Indiana, it would not apply
the people in New York because they have
a much more diverse population from
people from all over the world. If you
took what's the training that happened
in New York and applied it to Oklahoma,
it wouldn't work there either. So you
have to balance how the AI and have it
be specifically trained for your region.
And if you don't do that, you're going
to have better outcomes.
>> No, that's a that's a really important
thing as well. I I think we we're we're
definitely quick to trust. And I think
one of the things that concerns me most
is the bias from the not the standpoint
of somebody doing something on purpose.
It's that inadvertent miss that could
could occur. Whether it's making the
wrong assumption like we would do
between, you know, Oklahoma and New York
City, there's different needs and
different dynamics around the
communities, a lot of different factors
that that could make that very very
different. But there's also what's
missing. Uh, and that's another thing
that is is a concern because I know, you
know, I've talked about this before as a
physician. You don't know what you don't
know about me as your patient and you
don't know if what you don't know is
important and AI is not going to solve
that for us. So we have we definitely
need to be aware of it. I think it can
maybe reduce the odds of missing
information, but it's not going to
completely address that at all. So
that's a really great call out. If I
may, I I have one request for everyone.
Can we please fix the interoperability
problem?
Please. That's just really, really
simple. All of you who have ever
traveled around the world, you know that
you can go into an ATM machine, stick
your card in and get local currency. We
can do that. Now, I understand that
healthc care is much more complicated.
Our systems are more complicated. The
the nomenclature we use is more
complicated. But there's no reason that
a hospital one hospital in Boston, which
is less than a mile away from the other
hospital in Boston, the physician can't
see the MRI done in hospital A because
they're on a different system in
hospital B. An MRI is a standard format
that should easily be able to be
accessed and seen. Patients should be
able to download their MRI and and if
they need be put it on a disc on a thumb
drive on their phone and deliver it to
the other physician. That's a real
problem because it's not only expensive
for us to do this. We duplicate tests
patients. We misdiagnose patients
because we're missing it. But also we
don't have a data set that we can use to
train the II. Can't we just have one
standard data set that we can use and
have that interoperability happen? So, I
challenge those EMR companies. Can you
please fix this? It should not be this
hard. And oh, by the way,
>> the data belongs to the patient, not to
the hospital and not to the tech
company. It belongs to the patient and
they share it with you so you could do
good things with it, so you can develop
better systems. It's okay that you're
forprofit. It's okay that you make
money. That's fine. But recognize it's
the patient who's making the investment
to help you do that. So your
responsibility is to give back. How do
you give back? Produce great tools and
let's fix this interoperability problem.
>> I don't know if that could ever be said
more clearly. I I that is a huge issue
and I think anyone's been working
particularly in the IT or clinical
spaces over the last decade has seen so
many difficulties arise from not being
able to get access to the information
that you need. Um this is about saving
lives after all. So yeah, I think we
need to figure this out equally perhaps
more.
>> And what about saving money? And if we
are able to save money, we can do more
with that. We can be more efficient,
right? We have to get rid of the
friction that exists in healthcare. And
that's fine. Everybody can make their
profit. I'm okay with all of that. I'm a
capitalist day. That's good. But let's
do better. Doctors try to do better.
Nurses try to do better. The janitor in
the hospital works hard focused on right
make helping the hospital stay in a
pristine way that patients will not get
sick from hospital acquired infections.
Okay. So let's all try to do a little
bit better with this and I think we can.
There are ways for us to do this.
Wholeheartly agree.
I'm with you and as long as I get the
chance to to collaborate with you, I I'm
gonna be working on my end just as hard
as I can to help you solve this. I know
it's hugely important and if we can
leave a legacy of something valuable
that would be one massive contribution
and I think we could get a lot of people
aligned to help help us really push on
that. So I hope I hope we get the chance
to to really do some meaningful work
there together.
>> That would that would be great. Um I was
at a hem conference and the keynote
speaker uh Bit Stone uh started Twitter
back in the day and during his keynote
speech he said companies only have three
purposes.
>> Make money, do good, have fun. And let's
think about it,
>> right? You can make a lot of money and
be very successful doing good and having
fun. And there are examples of those
companies out there. And I think in
healthcare we can should do the same.
Let's do good. Let's have fun. And let's
make money. And we can do that.
>> Well said. I I love it. So if you could
give a piece of advice to health systems
uh CEOs and boards that might be reading
your book, what what would it be?
>> When we think of AI, we think it's
smart, but in reality, it's dumb. It
doesn't know anything. Has no opinions.
It's all statistical and probabilities.
You know who's smart? know who's
intelligent, know who's knowledgeable,
the person at the desk using the AI. So
my call to action for all of you is
recognize that your what makes AI
valuable and your knowledge, your
experience, your dedication, your goals,
your objectives, your morals, your
ethics is what should constrain and
direct AI in how it is used. So never
think that I'm going to use AI and it'll
solve my problem. Think I'm going to use
a tool like AI with my knowledge,
intelligence, strategies, values to
solve the problem. And without you, AI
can do nothing. It can hallucinate. It
can do misinformation. It can hurt
people. But with you, it can do great
things. So never forget, you're the
center of what m can make AI great. I
don't think there could be a better
public service announcement than what
you just gave it. It it it's such an
important message. I'm so glad that
you're saying this and I cannot wait for
our listeners to to hear this and I'm
going to go out on a limb. I think
they're going to read a lot more about
it, too. So, as we're kind of wrapping
up, I want to continue just a little bit
more on on on your your future of
healthcare 2050. What's one question you
hope every reader walks away asking
themselves after finishing reading this
book?
>> What can I do to
ensure
that the humanity vested in the word
trust gets applied to how AI is utilized
in my professional and personal life.
That is most important. Let's preserve
the trust and understand that humans
should control AI. AI should never
control us.
>> Excellent. Well, as we begin to wrap
here, Dr. Jacen, this show is all about
signals versus noise in healthcare
innovation. What's the clearest signal
that you're hearing right now and where
AI and healthcare is headed?
>> That's a difficult question because I
hear way too much noise, crazy ideas.
It's going to do ABC. It's going to take
over doctors. We're going to have a
hologram of a physician who's going to
take care of you. All of that. That's so
much of the the noise you hear. And I
think we reason why hear so much noise
is because people don't really
understand
AI and how it should be used. Last week
I spent time with two of my wonderful
longtime colleagues. One is teaches
management um at a local university. The
other one teaches environmental
engineering at a local university. And
I've been a guest lecturer in both of
their classes. And I speak to them about
AI, about things that I knew and
understood a year ago and they don't
know about. They tell me about their um
faculty deciding how students should be
utilizing AI. and my colleague and I
take our long walks and we do the usual
go back and forth of how should we use
it and try to evolve and develop and
build upon each other's ideas using the
AI. So that's so much there's so much
noise cuz we don't
most people don't understand it. What's
the signal? That's a hard one. The
signal is the AI itself is moving so
incredibly fast irrespective of
everything else that is absolutely
happening and it is happening at a pace
that keeps accelerating that even the
people who work in it don't know. So
let's ignore the noise, focus on the
signal and learn so we can understand
what the signal is and what it's telling
us. Where can listeners find your book,
follow your work or invite you to speak
further about this important topic. Uh
we've only scratched the surface. Um but
I know our listeners have have gotten a
ton of really great insight and I I
think you're going to need to make it
available. Tell them right where they
can get it because I think they're
they're going to be excited to read.
Well, you can find everything about me
at barrychin.com.
Uh, and in there you will you can have
some fun. Not only you can read about my
book, you can order a deluxe signed copy
there that I'll sign and if you want to
put a little uh message in to you and
that I can mail out to you. Um, it's
also available on Amazon and Barnes &
Noble, but obviously I can't sign them
there. Um, the second the second thing
is what I created was a little chatbot.
Two different types of chat bots. One of
them is you can text in it and that'll
appear on the the homepage as well as
there's a little menu here. You can go
to that and you can ask me questions.
But what I specifically did is if you
ask me what the weather is going to be
in your town next week, it'll
specifically say to you it's not my
database and I've been instructed not to
hallucinate. So I've made a point of
doing that. The second one is I also
created one where you could actually
quote unquote call me. You hit the
little call button. you can ask the same
question, it'll respond back to you in
my cloned voice. So, it's just a little
fun way how to use AI. And um I have a
lot of uh uh information on my website,
barrychin.com, but of course, you know,
feel free to reach out to me using that
site. And please connect with me on
LinkedIn. Um, it's barrychan.comln
and that'll uh link you up to LinkedIn
and my page and we can connect.
[music]